The first question is this.
السوال الأول هو.
Our country has two exploration programs.
يوجد فى الولايات المتحدة برنامجين للأستكشاف
One is NASA, with a mission to explore the great beyond,
الأول: برنامج ناسا و مهمته إكتشاف الخفايا العظيمة
to explore the heavens, which we all want to go to if we're lucky.
و البحث في السموات التي يرغب الجميع في الذهاب اليها لو صادفنا الحظ
And you can see we have Sputnik, and we have Saturn,
جميعكم يعرف القمر الصناعي "سبانيك" و "ساترن "
and we have other manifestations of space exploration.
و لدينا مظاهر أخرى من إكتشافات الفضاء
Well, there's also another program,
ولكن هناك أيضا برنامج أخر
in another agency within our government, in ocean exploration.
في وكالة أخرى داخل حكومة الولايات المتحدة, في أستكشاف المحيطات
It's in NOAA, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.
هى : "أن أو أ أ" الأدارة القومية للمحيطات و البيئة
And my question is this: "why are we ignoring the oceans?"
وسؤالي هو : لماذا نتجاهل المحيطات؟
Here's the reason, or not the reason, but here's why I ask that question.
وهذا هو السبب وراء سؤالي
If you compare NASA's annual budget to explore the heavens,
لو قارنت الميزانية السنوية ل "ناسا" لاستكشاف الفلك
that one-year budget would fund NOAA's budget
في سنة واحدة فهي تساوى ميزانية "ان أو أى أى"
to explore the oceans for 1,600 years.
لأكتشاف المحيطات مدة 1600 عام
Why? Why are we looking up? Is it because it's heaven?
لماذا؟! لماذا نحن ننظر للأعلى ؟! هل لأنها حيث الجنة !
And hell is down here? Is it a cultural issue?
و الجحيم في الأسفل هنا على الأرض! هل هي قضية ثقافية؟
Why are people afraid of the ocean?
لماذا يخاف الناس من المحيط؟
Or do they just assume the ocean is just a dark, gloomy place
هل هم يظنون أن المحيطات سوداء و كئيبة
that has nothing to offer?
وليس لديهم شىء ليقدموه؟
I'm going to take you on a 16-minute trip on 72 percent of the planet, so buckle up.
سوف أأخذكم في رحلة مدتها 16 دقيقة و تغطي 72% من الكرة الأرضية, فكونوا جاهزين
OK. And what we're going to do
ما سنقوم به الأن هو
is we're going to immerse ourselves in my world.
أننا سنعيش في عالمي -عالم المحيطات-
And what I'm going to try -- I hope I make the following points.
وما أحاول أن أعرضه عليكم اليوم
I'm going to make it right now in case I forget.
- أتمنى ألا أنسى
Everything I'm going to present to you
أي من النقاط التالية-
was not in my textbooks when I went to school.
غير موجود في الكتب المدرسية أثناء دراستي في المدرسة
And most of all, it was not even in my college textbooks.
وحتى في دراستي الجامعية لم أجد معظمها
I'm a geophysicist, and all my Earth science books when I was a student --
أنا جيوفيزيائي وأثناء دراستي, كل كتبي كانت عن علم الأرض
I had to give the wrong answer to get an A.
كان ضروري أجابة الأسئلة خطأ للحصول على أعلى الدرجات
We used to ridicule continental drift. It was something we laughed at.
نحن أعتادنا على أحتكار ظاهرة "زحزحة القارات". فقد كانت مزحة نضحك عليها!
We learned of Marshall Kay's geosynclinal cycle, which is a bunch of crap.
تعلمنا من نظرية "مارشل كاى", و كانت تعتبر حماقة!
In today's context, it was a bunch of crap,
في كلامنا اليومي, كانت حماقة
but it was the law of geology, vertical tectonics.
برغم من أنها كانت أساس علم الجيولوجيا.
All the things we're going to walk through
معظم الأشياء التي سنتكلم عنها
in our explorations and discoveries of the oceans
في تنقيبتنا و أكتشفاتنا للمحيطات
were mostly discoveries made by accident.
أكتشفت بالصدفة!
Mostly discoveries made by accident.
عادةً الأكتشافات تُكتشف بالصدفة
We were looking for something and found something else.
نحن نبحث عن شىء ونجد شىء أخر
And everything we're going to talk about
وكل شىء سنتكلم عنه
represents a one tenth of one percent glimpse, because that's all we've seen.
يمثل نسبة ضئيلة جدا لأن هذا هو ما أكتشفناه.
I have a characterization.
لديّ رؤيا للعالم.
This is a characterization of what it would look like if you could remove the water.
هذه رؤيا للعالم إذا أزالنا منه المياة
It gives you the false impression it's a map.
ربما تظن أنها خريطة للوهلة الأولى
It is not a map.
لكنها ليست خريطة
In fact, I have another version at my office
في الحقيقة, لديا أصدار أخر منها في مكتبي
and I ask people, "Why are there mountains here, on this area here,
وأسأل الناس, "لماذا توجد جبال في هذة البقعة
but there are none over here?" And they go, "Well, gee,
وليس في غيرها؟" فيردون
I don't know," saying,
"أنا لا أعلم!"
"Is it a fracture zone? Is it a hot spot?"
"ربما منطقة شقوق؟ " "ربما فهوه في باطن الأرض؟"
No, no, that's the only place a ship's been.
"لا! لا! هذه هي الأماكن التي مرت بها السفن من قبل".
Most of the southern hemisphere is unexplored.
النصف الجنوبي من الكرة الأرضية غير مكتشف بعد.
We had more exploration ships down there
نحن لدينا رحلات أستكشافية في زمن
during Captain Cook's time than now. It's amazing.
"كابتن كوك" أكثر من الأن. أليس هذا عجيب!
All right. So we're going to immerse ourselves
سوف نقوم بالتفكير في
in the 72 percent of the planet because, you know,
72% من الكرة الأرضية لأنكم كما تعلمون
it's really naive to think that the Easter Bunny
أنه من السذاجة أن "ميكي ماوس"
put all the resources on the continents.
وضع كل الموارد في كل القارات!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, it's just ludicrous.
بالفعل, هذا مثير للسخرية.
We are always, constantly playing the zero sum game.
و كأننا نعتبر الموارد الاقتصادية تتكون من كمية ثابتة
You know, we're going to do this, we're going to take it away from something else.
إذا اضفنا اليها جزء يجب أن نأخذ منها جزءًا أخر
I believe in just enriching the economy.
أنا أؤمن بإثراء الإقتصاد
And we're leaving so much on the table, 72 percent of the planet.
ولكننا تركنا 72% من الكرة الأرضية دون الإهتمام
And as I will point out later in the presentation,
وسوف أشير لاحقا إلى أن
50 percent of the United States of America lies beneath the sea.
50% من الولايات المتحدة تقع تحت البحار.
50 percent of our country that we own, have all legal jurisdiction,
هذا البلد لديه السلطة القضائية الكاملة
have all rights to do whatever we want, lies beneath the sea
لفعل أي شىء يريده يقع تحت البحار
and we have better maps of Mars than that 50 percent.
ونحن لدينا خرائط لكوكب المريخ أفضل من تلك المتاحة لهذه البحار
Why? OK. Now, I began my explorations the hard way.
لماذا؟ الأن, أنا بدأت في سرد أستكشافاتي.
Back then -- actually my first expedition
في الواقع, أول بعثاتي
was when I was 17 years old. It was 49 years ago.
كانت في سن 17 من عمري. منذ 49 عام.
Do the math, I'm 66. And I went out to sea on a Scripps ship
فبالحسابات, عمري 66عاما. كنت على أحدى سفن معهد أبحاث المحيطات
and we almost got sunk by a giant rogue wave,
و كنا على وشك الغرق نتيجة أحدى الموجات الضخمة
and I was too young to be -- you know, I thought it was great!
كنت صغيرا جدا وقتها و ظننت أنها موجة كبيرة!
I was a body surfer and I thought, "Wow, that was an incredible wave!"
تألمت كثيرا بعدها وفكرت قائلا" حقا, كانت موجة كبيرة"
And we almost sank the ship, but I became enraptured
لقد كنا على وشك الغرق ولكنى كنت مبتهج جدا
with mounting expeditions. And over the last 49 years,
بصعوبة المهمة. وخلال ال49 عام الأخير
I've done about 120, 121 -- I keep doing them -- expeditions.
قمت ب121 بعثة ولازلت أقوم بالبعثات الإستكشافية
But in the early days, the only way I could get to the bottom
منذ فترة طويلة, كانت الوسيلة الوحيدة للوصول الى القاع
was to crawl into a submarine, a very small submarine,
هي الغواصة, غواصة صغيرة جدا
and go down to the bottom.
و الغوص الى الأسفل.
I dove in a whole series of different deep diving submersibles.
لقد غصت في مختلف الأعماق وأماكن الغطس
Alvin and Sea Cliff and Cyana,
في مناطق "ألفين", "سى كليف" و "سيانا"
and all the major deep submersibles we have, which are about eight.
وفي أعمق الأماكن الممكنة للغطس وعددهم .8
In fact, on a good day, we might have four or five human beings
في الواقع, يوجد 4 ل 5 غطاسين في أفضل الأحوال
at the average depth of the Earth --
على عمق متوسط من سطح الارض
maybe four or five human beings out of whatever billions we've got going.
ربما 4 ل 5 أفراد من مليارات البشر !
And so it's very difficult to get there, if you do it physically.
لذلك القيام بهذه المهمات بدنياً يعتبر صعب للغاية
But I was enraptured, and in my graduate years
لكني كنت في غاية الإبتهاج, وفي سنوات تخرجى
was the dawn of plate tectonics. And we realized
أُكتشفت نظرية "الصفائح التكتونية". وأدركنا
that the greatest mountain range on Earth lies beneath the sea.
أن معظم الجبال الضخمة في العالم تقع تحت سطح البحر.
The mid-ocean ridge runs around like the seam on a baseball.
أن "حيود منتصف المحيط" يشبه الخياطة في كرة البيسبول
This is on a Mercator projection.
على مسقط "مركاتور" (إسقاط أسطواني)
But if you were to put it on an equal area projection,
ولكن لو وضعناها على مسقط يحافظ على تطابق وتساوى المساحة,
you'd see that the mid-ocean ridge covers 23 percent
فسوف نجد أن نتوءات منتصف المحيط تغطي 23%
of the Earth's total surface area.
من مساحة الأرض الكلية.
Almost a quarter of our planet is a single mountain range
بمعنى أن ربع مساحة كوكب الأرض هي سلسلة من الجبال.
and we didn't enter it until after Neil Armstrong
ونحن لم نكتشفها حتى غزى "نيل أرمسترونج"
and Buzz Aldrin went to the moon.
و"باز الدرين" القمر.
So we went to the moon, played golf up there,
فنحن ذهبنا الى القمر, ولعبنا الجولف هناك,
before we went to the largest feature on our own planet.
قبل إكتشاف أهم خصائص كوكبنا.
And our interest in this mountain range, as Earth scientists in those days,
وأهتمامنا بهذه الجبال, كما قام علماء هذا العصر,
was not only because of its tremendous size, dominating the planet,
ليس بسبب ضخامة حجمها
but the role it plays in the genesis of the Earth's outer skin.
ولكن لدورها في تكوين الطبقة الخارجية للأرض.
Because it's along the axis of the mid-ocean ridge
لأنها منطقة محور حيود منتصف المحيط
where the great crustal plates are separating.
حيث تتوسع طبقات ضخمة من القشرة الأرضية.
And like a living organism, you tear it open,
ومثل الكائنات الحية, عندما تصاب بجرح
it bleeds its molten blood, rises up to heal that wound
فينزف دمه الذائب ليحمي الجرح
from the asthenosphere, hardens, forms new tissue and moves laterally.
من طبقة"الأثينوسفير", ثم تتصلب وتكون أرض جديدة وبعدها تتحرك أفقيا.
But no one had actually gone down
ولكن لم يذهب أحد بالفعل
into the actual site of the boundary of creation as we call it --
الى مكان حدود الحياة -كما نسميها
into the Rift Valley -- until a group of seven of us
"وادي الشقوق"- حتى بدأت مجموعة مننا مكونة من 7 أفراد
crawled in our little submarines in the summer of 1973, 1974
بالأستكشاف بأستخدام الغواصات, صيف عام 1973-1974
and were the first human beings to enter the Great Rift Valley.
وكانوا من أوائل البشر الذين يدخلون هذا الوادي
We went down into the Rift Valley.
ونزلنا الى هذا الوادي
This is all accurate except for one thing -- it's pitch black.
لكن المشكلة الكبيرة هي الظلام الشديد
It's absolutely pitch black, because
بالتأكيد الظلام الشديد لأن
photons cannot reach the average depth of the ocean,
الفوتون (خلايا الضوء) لا تصل لمتوسط أعماق المحيطات
which is 12,000 feet. In the Rift Valley, it's 9,000 feet.
12000 قدم(3600متر), وفي "وادي الشقوق" العمق يصل الى 9000 قدم(2700متر)
Most of our planet does not feel the warmth of the sun.
معظم كوكب الأرض لا يشعر بالحرارة التي تصله من الشمس.
Most of our planet is in eternal darkness.
معظم كوكب الأرض في ظلام داخلي شديد.
And for that reason, you do not have photosynthesis in the deep sea.
ولهذا السبب لايوجد "تمثيل ضوئي" في عمق البحر.
And with the absence of photosynthesis
وبغياب "التمثيل الضوئي"
you have no plant life, and as a result,
لايوجد حياة للنباتات, ونتيجة لذلك
you have very little animal life living in this underworld.
يوجد حياة ضعيفة جدا للحيوانات في عالم البحار
Or so we thought. And so in our initial explorations,
ولذلك في بداية إستكشافاتنا
we were totally focused on exploring the boundary of creation,
كنا نركز تركيز تام على إستكشاف "مكان حدود الحياة"
looking at the volcanic features running along that entire 42,000 miles.
والنظر الى خصائص البراكين على طول 42000 ميل(74000متر)
Running along this entire 42,000 miles
على طول كل هذه أميال
are tens of thousands of active volcanoes.
يوجد آلاف من البراكين النشطة
Tens of thousands of active volcanoes.
عشرات آلاف من البراكين النشطة.
There are more active volcanoes beneath the sea
وهناك أعداد أكثر من البراكين النشطة في قاع المحيط
than on land by two orders of magnitude.
عن تلك التي على الأرض وبفارق كبير
So, it's a phenomenally active region,
لذلك فهي منطقة نشطة بطريقة غير أعتيادية
it's not just a dark, boring place. It's a very alive place.
فهي ليست مجرد ظلام. فهي منطقة حيوية جداً.
And it's then being ripped open.
ثم توسعت.
But we were dealing with a particular scientific issue back then.
ولكننا نتكلم بالأخص على الجانب العلمي.
We couldn't understand why you had a mountain under tension.
لم نستطع أن نفهم السبب وراء وجود الجبال تحت ضغط.
In plate tectonic theory, we knew that if you had plates collide,
في نظرية "الصفائح التكتونية" نحن نعلم أن الصفائح تتصادم,
it made sense: they would crush into one another,
وبالطبع, يندفعوا فوق بعضهم,
you would thicken the crust, you'd uplift it.
ولذلك ثخنت القشرة الأرضية, ثم تُرفع إلى أعلى.
That's why you get, you know, you get seashells up on Mount Everest.
وهذا هو السبب وراء وجود صدف البحر على قمة جبل "أفيرست"
It's not a flood, it was pushed up there.
لم يكن فيضان, لقد كانت أحدى الطبقات تحت الأرض ثم دُفعت للأعلى
We understood mountains under compression,
لقد فهمنا السبب أن الجبال تحت ضغط,
but we could not understand why we had a mountain under tension.
ولكننا لم نفهم لماذا تكون الجبال تحت قوة شد
It should not be. Until one of my colleagues said,
يفترض ألا يحدث ذلك. حتى قال أحد زملائي,
"It looks to me like a thermal blister, and the mid-ocean ridge
"أنى أرى أنها مثل فقاعة حرارة و نتوء منتصف المحيط
must be a cooling curve." We said, "Let's go find out."
هو الذي يبرد هذه الفقاعة". فبدأنا في البحث عن هذا الاحتمال.
We punched a bunch of heat probes. Everything made sense,
فقمنا بتوصيل حرارة في القشرة الأرضية هناك. ووجدنا بالفعل ما توقعناه
except, at the axis, there was missing heat. It was missing heat.
ماعدا في المحور وجدنا فقد فى الحرارة.
It was hot. It wasn't hot enough.
لقد كانت ساخنه ولكن ليس بالقدر الكافي.
So, we came up with multiple hypotheses:
لذلك استنتجنا بعض الافتراضات,
there's little green people down there taking it;
هناك بعض المحافظين على البيئة يبنون عليها.
there's all sorts of things going on.
أو ما شابه ذلك.
But the only logical [explanation] was that there were hot springs.
ولكن الحل المنطقي الوحيد هو وجود ينابيع مياه دافئة.
So, there must be underwater hot springs.
لذلك أصبح من المؤكد وجود ينابيع مياه دافئة.
We mounted an expedition to look for the missing heat.
فبدأنا حملة للبحث عن الفاقد في الحرارة
And so we went along this mountain range, in an area along Galapagos Rift,
و ذهبنا على طول الجبال في منطقة "صدع جالاباجوس".
and did we find the missing heat.
وبالفعل أكتشفنا الحرارة المفقودة.
It was amazing. These giant chimneys, huge giant chimneys.
لقد كانت رائعة. كانت عبارة عن مداخن متناهية الضخامة.
We went up to them with our submersible.
وصعدنا إليها بإستخدام الغواصات.
We wanted to get a temperature probe, we stuck it in there,
وأردنا أن نقيس درجة الحرارة, فوضعنا الثرمومتر
looked at it -- it pegged off scale.
فوجدنا أن الحرارة أعلى من قدرة الثرمومتر على القياس.
The pilot made this great observation: "That's hot."
فأستنتج الغواص أستنتاجاً خطيراً : "أنها ساخنة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then we realized our probe was made out of the same stuff --
ثم أدركنا أن الحرارة عالية للغاية.
it could have melted. But it turns out the exiting temperature
لقد كان على وشك الانصهار. وصلت الحرارة إلى
was 650 degrees F, hot enough to melt lead.
350 درجة مئوية, تكفي لأنصهار الرصاص.
This is what a real one looks like, on the Juan de Fuca Ridge.
كانت تشبه صدع "جوان دى فوكا"
What you're looking at is an incredible pipe organ
ما كنا نراه كان يشبه ماسورة كيماويات ضخمة للغاية
of chemicals coming out of the ocean.
تصب في المحيط.
Everything you see in this picture is commercial grade:
كل ما ترونه في الصورة هو منتجات صالحة للإستخدام في التجارة
copper, lead, silver, zinc and gold.
النحاس ,الرصاص ,الفضة ,الزنك والذهب
So the Easter Bunny has put things in the ocean floor,
فهل قام ميكي ماوس بوضع هذه الأشياء في قاع المحيط,
and you have massive heavy metal deposits
ولدينا احتياطيات ضخمة من المعادن الثقيلة
that we're making in this mountain range.
هنا في هذه السلسلة الجبلية.
We're making huge discoveries of large commercial-grade ore
لقد قمنا باكتشافات ضخمة لمعادن ثمينة صالحة للإستخدام في التجارة
along this mountain range, but it was dwarfed by what we discovered.
موجودة على هذه السلسلة من الجبال, ولكن حجمها يتضاءل بالنسبة لما أكتشفناه لاحقاً.
We discovered a profusion of life,
لقد أكتشفنا وجود الحياة بنطاق واسع
in a world that it should not exist [in]. Giant tube worms, 10 feet tall.
في عالم لا يمكن أن نجدها فيه. ماسورة ضخمة, ساخنة وطولها 3 أمتار.
I remember having to use vodka -- my own vodka -- to pickle it
أذكر حين أستخدمت الخمر لحفظها
because we don't carry formaldehyde.
لأننا لم يكن لدينا فورمالديهايد (مادة للحفظ)
We went and found these incredible clam beds
وجدنا أصداف ضخمة جداً
sitting on the barren rock. Large clams,
موضوعة على صخرة جرداء,
and when we opened them, they didn't look like a clam.
و عند فتحها, فهي لا تبدو كالأصداف.
And when we cut them open, they didn't have the anatomy of a clam.
ولكنها مختلفة تشريحيا عن الأصداف التقليدية.
No mouth, no gut, no digestive system.
الفم, الأمعاء والجهاز الهضمي غير موجودين.
Their bodies had been totally taken over
كل أجسامهم قد أنتزعت
by another organism, a bacterium, that had figured out
من كائن حي أخر, باكتريا, ثم لاحقاً أكتشفنا
how to replicate photosynthesis in the dark,
كيفية قيامها بعملية التمثيل الضوئي في الظلام
through a process we now call chemosynthesis.
من خلال عملية أطلقنا عليها لاحقاً "التمثيل الكيميائي"
None of it in our textbooks. None of this in our textbooks.
هذه المعلومات غير موجودة في مراجعنا.
We did not know about this life system.
نحن لم نكن نعرف نظام حياتهم.
We were not predicting it.
نحن لم نتنبأ بها.
We stumbled on it, looking for some missing heat.
لقد صادفتنا هذه الاكتشافات أثناء البحث عن الفقد في الحرارة.
So, we wanted to accelerate this process.
فأردنا تسريع هذه العملية.
We wanted to get away from this silly trip, up and down on a submarine:
لقد كانت عملية استخدام الغواصة للأعلى والأسفل سخيفة للغاية.
average depth of the ocean, 12,000 feet;
متوسط عمق المحيط 3600 متر,
two and half hours to get to work in the morning;
ساعتان ونصف للذهاب للعمل
two and half hours to get to home. Five hour commute to work.
ساعتان ونصف للعودة للمنزل. 5ساعات للذهاب والعودة للعمل يومياً.
Three hours of bottom time, average distance traveled -- one mile.
3ساعات للغطس مسافة 1ميل (1.6متر)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
On a 42,000 mile mountain range. Great job security, but not the way to go.
وأمام سلسلة جبال ضخمة تمتد لمسافة 12800 مترا. لقد كانت خطرة بالتأكيد.
So, I began designing a new technology of telepresence,
لذلك بدأت في تصميم تكنولوجيا جديدة للتواصل وكأنك موجود بالفعل
using robotic systems to replicate myself,
بأستخدام روبوتات (الرجل الآلي) لتقوم بدوري وكأنني موجود بالفعل,
so I wouldn't have to cycle my vehicle system.
فأصبحت غير مطالب بالقيام بالروتين اليومي السخيف.
We began to introduce that in our explorations,
وبدأنا أستخدام هذه التكنولوجيا في استكشافتنا,
and we continued to make phenomenal discoveries
فأستكملنا الأكتشافات المدهشة
with our new robotic technologies. Again, looking for something else,
بهذه التكنولوجيا الآلية الجديدة. ولكن تطلعنا إلى شىء آخر,
moving from one part of the mid-ocean ridge to another.
التحرك من مكان إلى آخر.
The scientists were off watch and they came across incredible life forms.
وأكتشف العلماء مخلوقات تعيش حياة غريبة بعد أن كانوا غافلين عنها.
They came across new creatures they had not seen before.
مخلوفات لم يروها من قبل.
But more importantly, they discovered
ولكن أهم ما أكتشفوه
edifices down there that they did not understand.
هو الصروح العظيمة الموجودة في المحيط
That did not make sense. They were not above a magma chamber.
التي لم يعرفوا كيف وجدت. لم تكن فوق أي تجويف منصهر.
They shouldn't be there. And we called it Lost City.
كيف وٌجدت هنا! فأطلقنا عليها أسم "المدينة المفقودة".
And Lost City was characterized by these incredible limestone formations
وهذه المدينة تميزت بوجود تكوينات مختلفة من الحجر الجيري
and upside down pools. Look at that.
وأحواض مقلوبة في قاع المحيط. أنظروا لهذه الصور.
How do you do that? That's water upside down.
ما أروعها ! كيف يمكن أن يحدث هذا ! هذا ماء مقلوب!
We went in underneath and tapped it, and we found that it had the pH of Drano.
فذهبنا إلى مستوى أعمق وصورنا هذه الصور, وعرفنا أن له تكوين قلوي.
The pH of 11, and yet it had chemosynthetic bacteria living in it
الرقم الهيدروجيني: 11 وبرغم من ذلك فهو لديه نوع من البكتريا - التي تعيش على التمثيل الكميائي - تعيش بداخله
and at this extreme environment.
وهذه طبيعة قاسية.
And the hydrothermal vents were in an acidic environment.
فالمخارج الحرارية في بيئة حمضية.
All the way at the other end, in an alkaline environment,
وفي الجانب الآخر هناك طبيعة قلوية
at a pH of 11, life existed.
والرقم الهيدروجيني هناك هو 11, والحياة موجودة.
So life was much more creative than we had ever thought.
إذن الحياة خلاقة أكثر مما نتوقع!
Again, discovered by accident. Just two years ago
مرة آخرى, أكتشفنا شىء آخر بالصدفة وكان ذلك منذ عامين فقط
working off Santorini, where people are sunning themselves on the beach,
في أحدى جزر اليونان (جزيرة سانتورينى) حيث يتشمس الناس على الرمال
unbeknownst to them in the caldera nearby,
وغير معلوم بالنسبة لهم أن في "الكالديرا" القريبة منهم - حفرة ضخمة نتيجة انفجارات بركانية-
we found phenomenal hydrothermal vent systems
ووجدنا فيها مخارج حرارية غير أعتيادية
and more life systems.
و الكثير من أنظمة الحياة المختلفة.
This was two miles from where people go to sunbathe,
لقد كانت على بعد 3200متر من الرمال حيث يتشمس الناس,
and they were oblivious to the existence of this system.
وكانوا غافلين عن هذه الاستكشافات العظيمة.
Again, you know, we stop at the water's edge.
مرة آخرى, توقفنا عند حدود الماء.
Recently, diving off -- in the Gulf of Mexico, finding pools of water,
في خليج المكسيك, ووجدنا أحواض من المياه
this time not upside down, right side up.
و لكنها ليست مقلوبة هذه المرة.
Bingo. You'd think you're in air, until a fish swims by.
ستظن أنك في الهواء عند النظر إلى هذه الصور حتى ترى الأسماك تسبح.
You're looking at brine pools formed by salt diapirs.
وأنت تنظر إلى أحواض مالحة تكونت من تأثير الأملاح على الصخور.
Near that was methane. I've never seen volcanoes of methane.
وقريباً من تلك الأحواض وجدنا غاز "الميثان". لم أرى في حياتي براكين من الميثان.
Instead of belching out lava, they were belching out
بدلاً من أن تقذف "حمم بركانية", تقذف فقاعات
big, big bubbles of methane. And they were creating these volcanoes,
كبيرة جداً من الميثان و يكونوا هذه البراكين,
and there were flows, not of lava,
حيث يتدفق معها طين الأرض
but of the mud coming out of the Earth but driven by --
بدلاً من الحمم البركانية.
I've never seen this before.
لم أرى شىءً كهذا من قبل!!
Moving on, there's more than just natural history beneath the sea --
ننتقل لنقطة آخرى, أن ألاكتشافات لم تكن طبيعية فقط,
human history. Our discoveries of the Titanic.
ولكنها كانت تحتوى على التاريخ الإنساني مثل اكتشاف سفينة "تايتنك".
The realization that the deep sea is the largest museum on Earth.
أدركنا بأن البحار العميقة هي أكبر متاحف العالم على الأرض
It contains more history than all of the museums on land combined.
فلديها تاريخ أكثر من متاحف العالم كله
And yet we're only now penetrating it.
ونحن لم نقم إلا بالقليل والظاهر حتى الأن.
Finding the state of preservation.
وجدنا أيضاً مدن كاملة محفوظة كما هي
We found the Bismarck in 16,000 feet. We then found the Yorktown.
وجدنا مدينة "بيسمارك" على عمق 4900 مترا. ثم وجدنا سفينة "يورك تاون"
People always ask, "Did you find the right ship?"
ويسأل الناس عادةً : "هل وجَدت السفينة الصحيحة؟"
It said Yorktown on the stern.
فأرد عليهم أن "يورك تاون" كانت مكتوبة على مؤخرة السفينة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
More recently, finding ancient history.
مؤخرا, وجدنا أشياء عن التاريخ القديم.
How many ancient mariners have had a bad day? The number's a million.
كم عدد البحارة القدامى الذين ماتوا غرقاً؟ العدد يصل لمليون!
We've been discovering these along ancient trade routes,
أكتشفنا ذلك على طول خطوط التجارة القديمة.
where they're not supposed to be.
حيث من المفترض ألا نجدهم.
This shipwreck sank 100 years before the birth of Christ.
هذه الحطام لسفينة غرقت قبل ميلاد المسيح ب100عام
This one sank carrying a prefabricated, Home Depot Roman temple.
وهذة الآخرى غرقت حاملة بعض الأدوات التي صنعت قديماً في معبد روماني.
And then here's one that sank at the time of Homer, at 750 B.C.
وآخرى غرقت في زمن الشاعر اليوناني "هوميروس" 750 قبل الميلاد.
More recently, into the Black Sea, where we're exploring.
وأيضاً مؤخراً, في البحر الأسود حيث كنا نستكشف
Because there's no oxygen there, it's the largest reservoir
وبسبب عدم وجود أوكسجين هناك - يعتبر أكبر خزان
of hydrogen sulfide on Earth. Shipwrecks are perfectly preserved.
ل "كبريتيد الهيدروجين" على الأرض. حطام السفن محفوظ على نحو تام.
All their organics are perfectly preserved. We begin to excavate them.
كل الكائنات العضوية محفوظة على نحو تام. وبدأنا في التنقيب عن هذه الأشياء.
We expect to start hauling out the bodies in perfect condition with their DNA.
وحدث ما توقعناه, كل الأجسام و حمضها النووى (DNA) التي سحبناها في حالة جيدة جداً
Look at the state of preservation --
أنظر إلى مدى الحفظ!
still the ad mark of a carpenter. Look at the state of those artifacts.
مازالت علامة النجار محفورة كما هي. أنظر إلى تلك القطع الأثرية!
You still see the beeswax dripping. When they dropped, they sealed it.
يمكنك رؤية شمع العسل يقطر. وعندما تتساقط تحتفظ بشكلها.
This ship sank 1,500 years ago.
هذه السفينة غرقت منذ 1500 عام.
Fortunately, we've been able to convince Congress.
لحسن الحظ, أستطعنا إقناع الكونجرس
We begin to go on the Hill and lobby.
بكافة الطرق والتأثير
And we stole recently a ship from the United States Navy.
وبالفعل أستولينا على سفينة من البحرية الأمريكية!
The Okeanos Explorer on its mission.
السفينة الإستكشافية "أوكينوس" أثناء أداء مهمتها
Its mission is as good as you could get.
ومهمتها أجمل المهمات
Its mission is to go where no one has gone before on planet Earth.
وهي أن تذهب حيث لم يذهب أحد قط.
And I was looking at it yesterday, it's up in Seattle. OK.
رأيتها في "سياتل" أمس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It comes online this summer,
وأصبحت في الخدمة صيف 2008
and it begins its journey of exploration.
وبدأت رحلتها الإستكشافية.
But we have no idea what we're going find when we go out there with our technology.
ولكننا لا نعلم ما سنكتشفه بأستخدام هذه التكنولوجيا.
But certainly, it's going to be going to the unknown America.
ولكن بالتأكيد سوف نبحث عن أمريكا المجهولة
This is that part of the United States that lies beneath the sea.
المساحات الشاسعة من الولايات المتحدة التي تقع تحت البحر
We own all of that blue and yet,
نحن نمتلك كل هذا الأزرق ولكن!
like I say, particularly the western territorial trust,
كما قلت, الوصاية الأقليمية الغربية!
we don't have maps of them. We don't have maps of them.
لا يوجد لدينا خرائط للمحيطات !
We have maps of Venus, but not of the western territorial trust.
لدينا خرائط لكوكب "الزهرة" وليس للملكية الغربية!
The way we're going to run this -- we have no idea what we're going to discover.
بالطريقة التي نتبعها في الإستكشاف
We have no idea what we're going to discover.
تجعلنا لا نعلم ماذا سنكتشف!
We're going to discover an ancient shipwreck, a Phoenician off Brazil,
سوف نكتشف حطام سفينة فينيقية قبالة سواحل البرازيل
or a new rock formation, a new life.
أو تكوينات صخور جديدة أو حياة جديدة أو غيرها.
So, we're going to run it like an emergency hospital.
فهي تشبه مستشفى طوارىء
We're going to connect our command center,
وسنربطها بمركز القيادة
via a high-bandwidth satellite link to a building we're building
- بأستخدام قمر صناعي عالي التردد -
at the University of Rhode Island, called the Interspace Center.
في مبنى يسمى "مركز أنترسبيس" بجامعة "رود ايلاند"
And within that, we're going to run it just like you run a nuclear submarine,
وسوف نشغلها بنفس طريقة تشغيل الغواصات النووية,
blue-gold team, switching them off and on, running 24 hours a day.
فريق متخصص, يعمل 24 ساعة في اليوم بنظام الورديات
A discovery is made, that discovery is instantly seen
لو اكتشف أى شىء, يُلاحظ فوراً
in the command center a second later.
وبعدها بثانية, يُلاحظه مركز القيادة.
But then it's connected through Internet too --
وسيلة الإتصال هي الإنترنت.
the new Internet highway that makes Internet one
نحن نستخدم الإنترنت عالي السرعة الذي يسمح بتداول
look like a dirt road on the information highway --
المعلومات وكأنها مطروحة في محتوى لهذه المعلومات
with 10 gigabits of bandwidth.
و بتردد عالي جداً يصل ل 10 جيجا بيت في الثانية.
We'll go into areas we have no knowledge of.
سوف نكتشف مناطق ليس لنا سابق معرفة عنها.
It's a big blank sheet on our planet. We'll map it within hours,
إنها مسطح ضخم جداً في كوكبنا. سوف نرسم له خارطة في غضون ساعات,
have the maps disseminated out to the major universities.
ونرسلها إلى الجامعت الرائدة.
It turns out that 90 percent of all the oceanographic intellect
وتبين لنا أن 90% من علم المحيطات
in this country are at 12 universities. They're all on I-2.
في الولايات المتحدة في 12 جامعة فقط. وجميعهم في منظمة I-2.
We can then build a command center.
فبنينا مركز قيادة.
This is a remote center at the University of Washington.
هذا مركز القيادة في جامعة واشنطن.
She's talking to the pilot. She's 5,000 miles away, but she's assumed command.
إنها تتحدث إلى القبطان. وبرغم من أنها على بعد 5000 ميل منه ولكنها تتحكم في القيادة.
But the beauty of this, too, is we can then disseminate it to children.
وأجمل ما في هذه التكنولوجيا هي قدرتنا على نشرها بين الأطفال.
We can disseminate.
نعم يمكننا.
They can follow this expedition. I've started a program --
يمكنهم متابعة هذة البعثات الإستكشافية. وقد بدأتُ هذا البرنامج بالفعل.
where are you Jim? Jim Young who helped me start a program
أين أنت يا "جيم"؟ (مزحة). "جيم يونج" كان أول من ساعد في بداية مشروع
called the Jason Project. More recently, we've started a program
يسمى "مشروع جاسون". بدأنا مؤخراً أحد البرامج
with the Boys and Girls Clubs of America,
مع الأولاد والبنات في النوادي الأمريكية
so that we can use exploration,
بحيث نستطيع إستخدام المستكشف البحري
and the excitement of live exploration, to motivate them and excite them
وجاذبية البث المباشر لها, لحثهم وتحميسهم
and then give them what they're already ready for.
وتقديم المادة الجاذبة التي يبحثون عنها.
I would not let an adult drive my robot.
لن أسمح لشاب أن يقود غواصتي!
You don't have enough gaming experience.
ليس لديك الخبرة الكافية في الألعاب الإلكترونية .
But I will let a kid with no license take over control of my vehicle system.
ولكنى سأسمح لطفل دون رخصة أن يتحكم فى غواصتي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Because we want to create --
لأننا نرغب في الأبداع.
we want to create the classroom of tomorrow.
يمكننا أبتكار طريقة التدريس للمستقبل.
We have stiff competition and we need to motivate and it's all being done.
لدينا منافسة صعبة, وعلينا أن نُحمس الشباب
You win or lose an engineer or a scientist by eighth grade.
نحن نخسر عالم أو مهندس في الصف الثامن من التعليم الأساسي
The game is not over -- it's over by the eighth grade, it's not beginning.
الصف الثامن ليس بداية للتعليم ولكننا نخسر الطلاب إذا أعتبرنا أنها كذلك.
We need to be not only proud of our universities.
نحن نريد أن نكون فخورين ليس بجامعتنا فقط
We need to be proud of our middle schools.
بل بمدارسنا أيضاً.
And when we have the best middle schools in the world,
وعندما تمتلك أفضل مدارس في العالم,
we'll have the best kids pumped out of that system, let me tell you.
سنحصل على أفضل أطفال من هذا النظام التعليمي, دعني أقول لك.
Because this is what we want. This is what we want.
لأن هذا ما نرغب به.
This is a young lady, not watching a football game,
هذه فتاة, لا تشاهد مبارة كرة قدم,
not watching a basketball game.
ولا تشاهد مبارة كرة سلة,
Watching exploration live from thousands of miles away,
بل تشاهد البث المباشر للبعثة الأستكشافية على بعد آلاف الأميال,
and it's just dawning on her what she's seeing.
هذه الفتاة تحاول أدراك ما تراه.
And when you get a jaw drop, you can inform.
وفي هذه الحالة يكون التعليم جذاباً
You can put so much information into that mind, it's in full [receiving] mode.
يمكنك تزويد هذة العقول المنبهرة بالكثير من المعلومات.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This, I hope, will be a future engineer
أتمنى أن تنجب هذه الطرق في التعليم مهندسين أو علماء للمستقبل
or a future scientist in the battle for truth.
يحاربون من أجل الحق.
And my final question, my final question --
وسؤالي الأخير, سؤالي الأخير
why are we not looking at moving out onto the sea?
لماذا لا نفكر في الهجرة إلى البحر؟
Why do we have programs to build habitation on Mars,
لماذا لدينا برامج للإستيطان في المريخ,
and we have programs to look at colonizing the moon,
وبرامج آخرى لإستعمار القمر,
but we do not have a program looking at how we colonize our own planet?
ولا يوجد برامج لإستعمار كوكبنا ؟
And the technology is at hand.
والتكنولوجيا متاحه لنا.
Thank you very much.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)